A Guide to the Anna Banana Collection, 1975-2003
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
The Anna Banana Collection 1975-2003
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 385
0.42 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Rebecca Dobyns.
The Anna Banana Collection was compiled by a former Special Collections and Archives intern, Rebecca Dobyns, in 2004. The stamps in the collection are also a gift sent directly from Anna Banana.The papers were collected by Dobyns as part of a book art project called To and From: Davi Det Hompson Correspondents. Her research was included in her master's thesis entitled "The Postcard Art Project." Dobyns is now a librarian in Henrico County.
Biographical Information
Anna Banana (b. 1940), formerly Anne Lee Long, is a visual and performance artist from Canada. Since the 1970s, she has been a major contributor and innovator of mail art. For over 30 years, she has been part of the International Mail Art Network (IMAN), an art exchange program that involves artists from all over the world. She has also published extensively on art related topics, including a newsletter called Banana Rag (1971-1991), which she converted into Artistamp News (1991-1996). In addition to her work with mail art, Anna Banana is also a performance artist. Her stage performances have included Dada and Futurist scripts as well as conceptual performances. *For more information, consult the Special Collections and Archives website http://www.library.vcu.edu/jbc/speccoll/davidet.html
Scope and Content
The collection consists of one box of thirty-one folders, which contains Anna Banana's extensive curriculum vitae, bibliographic materials, stamp designs from 1988-2002, selected newsletters from Banana Rag and Artistamp News, as well as reviews from various artists.
Arrangement
The collection has been divided into three groups: Artist's bibliographic materials, Newsletters, and Published articles on Anna Banana.
Contents List
- Artist's Bibliographic Materials n.d., 1988-2003, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Back Issues of Mail Art Publications Still Available from Banana Productions n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Curriculum Vitae October 2003 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Miscellaneous Advertisements 1994-2003 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Selected Bibliography n.d. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Stamp Collection 1988-2002 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Transportable, Berlin Exhibition Brochure April 13-May 11, 2003 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - To and From: Devi Det Hompson Correspondents, taken from Special Collections and Archives website July 30, 2007 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Newsletters 1987-90, 1993-96, 2003-04 (Box 1)
  - Artistamp News, Vol. 3, no. 1-2 February 1993 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Artistamp News, Vol. 4, no. 2 October 1994 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Artistamp News, Vol. 5, no. 1 June 1995 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Artistamp News, Vol. 6, no. 1 February 1996 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Banana Rag, No. 19 January 1987 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Banana Rag, No. 20 April 1987 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Banana Rag, No. 21 September 1987 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Banana Rag, No. 22 March 1988 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Banana Rag, No. 23 August 1988 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Banana Rag, No. 24 December 1988 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Banana Rag, No. 25 May 1989 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Banana Rag, No. 26 October 1989 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Banana Rag, No. 27 February 1990 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Banana Rag, No. 31 June 2003 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Banana Rag, No. 32 July 2004 (Box-folder 1:22)
- Published Articles on Anna Banana 1975, 1990, 1998-2000, 2002-03 (Box 1)
  - "The Banana Olympics" in San Francisco Bay Guardian 1975 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Rubberstampmadness, Vol. II no. 51 May/June 1990 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - "She's Going Bananas Over Private Stamps" in British Columbia Talks Business, Vol. 3, no. 1 1990 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - "It's Not So Easy Being Yellow," in The Globe and Mail August 20, 1998 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - "Special Delivery Brings Mail Art" in The Georgia Straight October/November 1999 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - National Post April 25, 2000 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - "Banana Art" in Times Colonist October 7, 2000 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - "Mail Art and Postal Art; the Difference in the Intention," by Anna Banana March 2002 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - "Anna Banana Visits York House!" in The Blackwatch November 2003 (Box-folder 1:31)